<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A muzzle for Cerberus, and his three vvhelps Mercurius Elencticus, Bellicus, and Melancholicus: barking against patriots &amp; martialists, in the present reign of their unwormed rage. With criticall reflections, on the revolt of Inchequin in Ireland. / By Mercurio-Mastix Hibernicus. ...</title>
            <author>Mercurio-Mastix Hibernicus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 91 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89434</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing M3166</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E449_3</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99861393</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99861393</idno>
            <idno type="VID">161846</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89434)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 161846)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 71:E449[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A muzzle for Cerberus, and his three vvhelps Mercurius Elencticus, Bellicus, and Melancholicus: barking against patriots &amp; martialists, in the present reign of their unwormed rage. With criticall reflections, on the revolt of Inchequin in Ireland. / By Mercurio-Mastix Hibernicus. ...</title>
                  <author>Mercurio-Mastix Hibernicus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 38 [i.e. 30] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Smithurst, and are to be sold neer Hosier-Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Partly in verse.</note>
                  <note>P. 30 misnumbered 38.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 20th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Inchiquin, Murrough O'Brien, --  Earl of, 1614-1674 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-05</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:161846:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A MUZZLE FOR CERBERUS, and his three VVhelps Mercurius <hi>Elenticus, Bellicus,</hi> and <hi>Melancholicus:</hi> Barking againſt Patriots &amp; Martialiſts, in the preſent reign of their <hi>unwormed rage.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With Criticall reflections, on the revolt of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chequin</hi> in <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Mercurio-Maſtix Hibernicus.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <head>To every unpartiall Reader, Cleare and Candid, without prejudicate Opinion.</head>
               <l>OH! be not prepoſſeſt (as much I feare)</l>
               <l>With a foreſtall'd opinion, as no eare,</l>
               <l>Nor eye to lend, this Antidote ſwift flying</l>
               <l>On paper wings, againſt three <hi>Mercuries</hi> lying:</l>
               <l>(For in all books, prejudicate opinions,</l>
               <l>Doe baine the beſt of all the <hi>Muſes</hi> Minions.)</l>
               <l>Let not thy wits in wilde-Gooſe chaſe ſo wander,</l>
               <l>As not to tract the paths of <hi>Alexander.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who ever ſuch unpartiall Juſtice uſed,</l>
               <l>To keep one eare for him who was accuſed.</l>
               <l>As a wiſe man, hear then both parties ſpeak:</l>
               <l>So ſhalt thou try Wolves bark, yea Rats who ſqueak,</l>
               <l>From bleats of Lambs, from moanes of mournfull Doves.</l>
               <l>Pure Gold from tinckling braſſe, the touch-stone proves.</l>
               <l>When Steeles and Flints be ſmit, the fire comes forth,</l>
               <l>So in croſſe tones, the truth here vents true worth.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <hi>London</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Smithurſt,</hi> and are to be ſold neer <hi>Hoſier-Lane,</hi> 1648:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:161846:2"/>
            <head>In laudem Authoris, Et in fraudem deriſoris.</head>
            <l>THanks to thy paines: I ſpeak it to thy praiſe,</l>
            <l>I ne'r read moe ſtrong lines, ſpun in two daies,</l>
            <l>So many quoted Authors, mixt with wit</l>
            <l>And judgement, in ſhort ſpace, I ſcarce view'd yet.</l>
            <l>Thy learned truth, the lying ſpirit hath ſhamed,</l>
            <l>Of a poore ſneak, not worthy to be named:</l>
            <l>I put thee on this task; thou haſt repeld them,</l>
            <l>In forty houres, thy night or dayes pains queld them.</l>
            <l>In truth I doe not flatter thee at all,</l>
            <l>Awalking Library, if I thee call.</l>
            <l>Its fit thy meritting worth ſhould be rewarded,</l>
            <l>And thy ſtrong active parts and pains regarded.</l>
            <l>If any <hi>Whale</hi> or <hi>Otter</hi> vent, the like</l>
            <l>To this, thy pen-ſpear, his fond head can ſtrike.</l>
            <closer>
               <signed>M. J.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:161846:2"/>
            <p>AS an Antidote againſt Cavilling Cavilliering exception, ready to finde a knot in a ſtreight ruſh, or as Mice and Rats in walls, and Apes and Monkies in pure lawnes, to make or rend holes where they finde none; leſt I miſtake in the number of theſe railing <hi>Rabſhakehs:</hi> I muſt confeſſe, I am a doubting Sceptick, and an unreſolved Didimiſt, whether onely one furious fantaſticke make his three fooles bolts which he throwes (as ſometimes <hi>Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſites</hi> againſt <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>liſſes, Semei</hi> againſt <hi>David, Rabſhakeh</hi> againſt <hi>Hezekias, Scopius</hi> againſt King <hi>James,</hi> and <hi>Endemon</hi> or <hi>Cacodemon,</hi> againſt our worthieſt Peers and Church lights) in the very face of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentary Patritians of our ſtate, and againſt the <hi>Militia</hi> in his <hi>malitia</hi> flying bird alone, as an <hi>individuum vagum,</hi> or a Woodcock in a miſt of ignorance; or rather like one <hi>Goliah</hi> defying the hoſt of Iſrael, it being ſomething probable that here we finde the tongue and tooth but of one <hi>Cerberus</hi> with three heads, or of one monſtrous <hi>Chimera</hi> in three ſhapes; like one eccho (compoſed like this wordy work of wind and aire) oft reſonating and redoubling three or four ſounds, as one babbling <hi>Battus</hi> and verbaliſt, three or foure words to as ſmall purpoſe, as the ſounding of an empty Hogſhead: Or that there be three Rakehells twiſting and twining this their rope Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricke to choke or ſtrangle our beſt Patriots, with their three pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per cords, as the Turkiſh mutes oft the beſt of Baſhawes with their halters, at the meer luſt for Law of their tyrannizing Ottomans: but the matter is but like a matter of Moon-ſhine in the water, whether one Moon-calfe here bleat in three libels, one Aſſe brey, one Wolfe howle, and one Owle houte againſt the ſhining Sun of Magiſtracy and Miniſtery, high Court and Campe; or there bee three Curs all barking, or three Maſtive dogs, like Butchers dogs with bloody mouthes, biting and ſnarling at emulated Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie; as like one another in their ſtigmatizing ſtile, as <hi>John a Nokes</hi> in the ſame caſe and cauſe to <hi>John a Stiles;</hi> or as a Snake to Snake, Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent to Serpent, Viper to Viper, all ſtinging the breaſts that have bred them, and fed them.</p>
            <p>All three (if three) led like <hi>Ahabs</hi> falſe Prophets in their vain pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gnoſticks by one deluding ſpirit, al birds of one black &amp; bloody fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, all frogs croaking one tone out of the infernall pit; all broken bels better for hanging, ringing of the ſame peale in their large and looſe appeales (like Libertines) from all Parliamentary Lawes; all like Armenian Dragons ſpitting fire, with tongues ſet on fire by
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:161846:3"/>
hell, more flamivorous then the Northerne <hi>Hecla,</hi> the Sicilian <hi>Aeina,</hi> or that <hi>Veſuvus</hi> which choaked the good Patriot <hi>Pliny;</hi> all like <hi>Simeon</hi> and <hi>Levi</hi> brethren in iniquity, never a barrell better Herring, all fellows well met at foot-ball, even to make foot-balls (if curſt cowes like <hi>Jezabel</hi> one againſt <hi>Elias,</hi> and the Arrians againſt <hi>Athana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> had not ſhort hornes) even of our wiſeſt and worthieſt heads, even ſuch ſpurned Bulls as cruell <hi>Scilla</hi> made of the head of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Mark Anthony</hi> of the head of <hi>Tully</hi> that eloquent ſpeaker, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grateful <hi>Ptolomy</hi> and <hi>Scep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nius</hi> the head of their beſt deſerving friend undaunted <hi>Pompey;</hi> but if they plead that they know not one another: Sure if ſimilitude be the cauſe of love, and the adomant of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, they may be acquainted without a couple of Capons, as ſoon as the Devill with the Collier, they are ſo like, that they cannot but ſay (when they meet at Dawes croſſe, or in Knaves alley, or in Toſpot alley, like kinde Poetaſters or pot taſters) <hi>ego novi ſinonem &amp; ſinon novit me;</hi> its merry when knaves meet, to keep <hi>Hillary</hi> Tearme, <hi>Cica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da, Cicadae, Chara,</hi> one Graſhopper and Creckit cleats to another <hi>mulus mulum ſcabit,</hi> one ſcab'd mule knaps another, &amp; <hi>graculus aſſidit graculo,</hi> one jaw jangles with another; we ſing all one ſong, though cleane out of tune, as that ungratefull ſcabgooke; the Cuccow in June, after ſhe have torne (like our Church and State Vipers) the kinde bird who bred her and fed her: yea I ſay more, though theſe three <hi>junior Rabſhekah's,</hi> ſhould be as ſnarling heretofore one againſt another as hounds in a kennell, or in couples, yet as they are united <hi>Nimrods</hi> in hunting to the very death, if they could, the moſt honourable and noble blood which runs in the veynes of both Houſes, with bloody pens and tongues (till they get <hi>Cains</hi> ſword, and <hi>Herods</hi> axe, for all innocuous <hi>Johns, Naboths</hi> and <hi>Abels</hi>) me thinks <hi>eo nomine,</hi> even this tye of fraternity in villany, ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile them, as much as ever <hi>Herod</hi> and <hi>Pilate</hi> againſt Chriſt. <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>im</hi> and <hi>Manaſſes</hi> againſt <hi>Judah,</hi> Jeſuits, Prieſts, and Fryers, againſt true Proteſtants, Antinomians, Socinians, Familiſts, Arminians, and other Heretickes, all againſt the orthodox and true believers, how ever different all amongſt themſelves, like the heads of the ſerpent <hi>Amphis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ena,</hi> one fighting againſt another (as indeed Bees a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree together in one hive, Piſmires in one moſſie hill; yea <hi>ſevis inter ſe convenit urſis,</hi> Beares in one cave; Foxes in woods, yea in Townes, in ſheeps cloathing; in Cities in fox fur gownes, yet all againſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent Lambes) as Devills agree together in one hell, and their a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gents, and Jeſuitized, Achitophilized, Hammanized, Papized,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:161846:3"/>
Athized working tooles on earth, as <hi>Tobiah</hi> the Ammonite, and <hi>Sanballat</hi> the Horonite, and <hi>Geſhem</hi> the Arabian againſt our <hi>Ezraes</hi> and <hi>Nebemiahs</hi> &amp; the Elders of Iſrael, to hinder the re-edifying of our Jeruſalem, the Reformation of Religion, and the repairing, &amp; pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging of our Temples, <hi>Neb.</hi> 2. 19. &amp; 6. 2. as the Scribes and Phariſees, and Saduces, and Herodians, ſtill againſt Chriſt and his Diſciples, his true Miniſters and his Meſſengers, as the Syrians, the Ammonites, and the Moabites, againſt every zealous <hi>Jehoſaphat, 2 Chr</hi> 20. 2. as the Elders of the people, the Prieſts, and my Lord <hi>Paſhur</hi> whilom a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Jeremy,</hi> to impriſon his body, to ſmite him with the tongue, and not to hearken to his words, <hi>Jer.</hi> 18. 18. (more then Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes, Epiſcopiſts, and deafe adders now, to ſuch true Seers, and Prophets, as God hath ſent and ſet amongſt us) all that beare evill unto Sion, and that hate to be reformed, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 50. now being tyed and combined together like <hi>Sampſons</hi> foxes, with firebrands in their tailes and in their tongues too, to fire our Church and State in new raiſed combuſtions, as we may ſee the nature of every other Fox and Malignant wolfe in the Church even in theſe now, who by their lewd Libells, and poyſonous Pamphlets, have caſt aſperſions both upon our Senators and Synod, as foule as falſe, to bring them in contempt with the fluctuate and credulous mutable multitude, who will believe their eares in a manner before their eyes, and take up ought like a ball at rebound, and ſnugge in any ſcandall, chiefly againſt great men and good men their ſuperiours, though they knew the Devill were the author of it, or his hell hatched Semina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, like theſe lying <hi>Mercuries:</hi> with whom to grapple a little cloſer.</p>
            <p>Firſt, I wonder they bluſh not, as they would, if they had not impudent harlots browes of braſſe, and foreheads of iron, to ſtum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſo foule at the threſhold (as <hi>Craſſus</hi> did when he went his fatall expedition againſt the Parthians, and <hi>Caeſar</hi> to the Senate where he was ſtabd, even in the Title wherewith they chriſtned the ſpurious brats of their braines with the name of <hi>Mercury,</hi> which <hi>Mercury</hi> if we believe Poets or Hiſtorians, was as very a Thiefe, as <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yron,</hi> or <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us,</hi> or our Engliſh <hi>Luke Hutton</hi> and <hi>Mannering,</hi> or any of our Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carriers in theſe late wars (though now of the <hi>Haſtings,</hi> deſerving a <hi>Newcaſtle</hi>) with all he was a cheater, and a lyer, a couzener, and an impoſter, like the Turkiſh Mahomet, the Spaniſh <hi>Guſman, Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rillo de Tormes,</hi> and our moſt nimble Troynovant City <hi>Sinons,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides he was <hi>euripus homo</hi> a wavering wimble, a fluctuate fellow, an unconſtant weathercocke, ſuited as a temporizer for all perſons
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:161846:4"/>
and places, as the plannet <hi>Mercury</hi> is ſaid to be good with the good, and bad with the bad, like our Mercurialized newters, Diſciples with Diſciples, and Traytors with Phariſees, as once <hi>Judas;</hi> ſoft wax fit for any impreſſion, and white paper fit for any print, as Camelions for any colour but white (being every thing but honeſt.) Fourthly, as <hi>Hermes</hi> was one of the names of <hi>Mercury,</hi> joyned with <hi>Aphrodite,</hi> ſignifying the Sea foame, one of the Epithites of <hi>Venus,</hi> there was produced a kinde of maſculine feminine monſter, called <hi>Hermo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phrodite</hi> (like ſome Harres and Hienaes) neither male, nor female, but both, as theſe our <hi>Mercuries</hi> are: as we ſay of archized Buffons and Tarltoniſts, neither knaves, nor fooles, but both; as a mule is neither an Horſe nor an Aſſe, but both; a Cynecepholiſt neither Ape nor Dog, but both; a Meer-maid neither fiſh nor fleſh, but both; <hi>mulier formoſa ſuperne deſine as in piſcem:</hi> thus like ſome Popes in their own uſurped names, theſe <hi>Chaiphaſſes</hi> or Catiffes, have propheſied trulier of themſelves then they wiſt; <hi>Naball</hi> is a name, and folly is in it; and <hi>Mercury</hi> is their name, and lying, and leizing, and colouging, and rouging, and diſſembling is in it, as in that grand Impoſtor the Aegyptian <hi>Moſes,</hi> and <hi>Bencosba</hi> the ſon of lying in <hi>Joſephus,</hi> and in theſe <hi>Pſeudo</hi> Princes recorded in the ſame <hi>Joſephus, lib. 17. cap. 14. antiq.</hi> and in <hi>Melancton</hi> Chronicle <hi>lib. 4: p.</hi> 358. and in <hi>Tacitus lib. 18. pag.</hi> 587. and in <hi>Munſters</hi> Coſmography <hi>pag.</hi> 171. who tooke upon them the names of great Potentates, though they were but Peaſants, <hi>Se conveniunt rebus nomina ſepe ſuis,</hi> as which Reſetters, Thieves have ſym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pathies, ſo to their names anſwer our <hi>Mercuries.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, as <hi>Mercury</hi> an Outlandiſh drug, is as ranke poyſon as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Ratsbaine or Henbaine, or Cicuta, or Bulls-blood that poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoned <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> or any other poyſons not worth naming, by which the Athenians poyſoned <hi>Socrates</hi> and <hi>Phocion,</hi> Queene <hi>Elinor,</hi> faire <hi>Roſamond,</hi> the Roman <hi>Calphurinus</hi> his ſleeping wives, and Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> and his Baſtard <hi>Borgias</hi> themſelves, inſtead of ſome Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls: ſo there is as much tongue-venome and poyſon dropt from the pens of theſe our lying libelling <hi>Mercuries,</hi> as there were diſeaſes in the opened <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anidraes</hi> box, or armed Greekes in the Trojan horſe to the intended ruination of all true Trojans, loyall Patricians in the Senate, and godly well-affected Miniſters in the Synod: yea I adde more, As Mercury is a poyſoned drug, though incloſed in a gawdy Apothecaries box, or given like <hi>Jaels</hi> butter to <hi>Sicera</hi> in a Lordly diſh; or in the Sacramentall bread or wine, as the Monkes once ſo poyſoned King <hi>John</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> and <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, an
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:161846:4"/>
Emperour of <hi>Germany;</hi> So theſe and ſuch like mercurialized Scy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cophants, how did they flatter regallity, and ſooth it up to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limited tranſcendency, in a Perſian and Turkiſh trampling upon all Lawes humaine, divine, naturall, nationall, and municipall, being like <hi>Craterus</hi> rather friends to <hi>Alexanders</hi> fortunes as a King, then to his perſon like <hi>Epheſtion;</hi> yet for all their dawbings, and ſowing cuſhions under their elbowes, like their Court Chaplaines, they give them but poyſoned pills in ſugar: <hi>Joabs</hi> kiſſes, <hi>Judaſſes,</hi> Haile Maſter, and <hi>Ravillacks</hi> Jeſuitized cringes, with a rotten heart, and oft a truculent hand; they doe but pave their way, as <hi>Damocles</hi> to <hi>Dioniſius</hi> to injuſtice, cruelty, and uſurpation, yea to their owne acted Tragedies, as with oyle and butter; they doe but hang them (as once <hi>Darius</hi> had prepared) with golden halters, ſtab them as with <hi>Heliogabulus</hi> his golden knives, ſting them as the Serpent <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantula</hi> lurking in green graſſe till they die laughing, claw them as Tygers to mollifie them to themſelves, &amp; to put the ſpur of oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to all others; as <hi>Patritius</hi> in his ſecond Booke of a Kingdome, <hi>tit. 1. pag.</hi> 82. and he that writes the Politicall Courtier, <hi>pag.</hi> 82. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve their owne queſtions? What made <hi>Nero</hi> ſo well educated by <hi>Seneca,</hi> ſo cruell? <hi>Caeſar</hi> ſuch an uſurping Rebell againſt his owne Country? <hi>Rehoboam</hi> ſo ſterne and auſtere? <hi>Tygranes</hi> the King of <hi>Pontus</hi> ſo tyrannicall, ere the Romans curbed him: in one word, their verdict is to every query, <hi>adulatio, adulatio,</hi> flattery, flattery? Mercurialized flattery (which though at firſt, like ſweet poyſons, it be pleaſing to the pallat, yet at laſt, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſpeakes of wine and women, <hi>Prov. 9. 17. 18. &amp; cap.</hi> 23. 32. it ſtings like a Serpent and bites like an Adder, which cauſed <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperour, as <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancton</hi> hath it in his Chronicles (<hi>lib. 5. pag.</hi> 630.) to hit a flatterer a good boxe on the eare, with this <hi>memento, Cur me mordes,</hi> why doſt thou bite me, and cauſed <hi>Zerpes</hi> ſaith <hi>Strigellus</hi> in his Chronicles <hi>part. 2. pag.</hi> 119. to deſire <hi>Demaratus</hi> a wiſe Counſellour ever to ſpeake to him, rather <hi>vera,</hi> things that might profit him, then <hi>jucunda,</hi> delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome things to pleaſe him: This cauſed alſo <hi>Attila</hi> the King of the <hi>Huns,</hi> to caſt ſome ſcycophantizing Poems of the <hi>Calabrian</hi> Poet <hi>Marulus</hi> into the fire, in which he had too hyperbolically extolled him: <hi>Antigonus</hi> for the ſame cauſe, ſaith <hi>Tholoſanus</hi> in his Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, <hi>lib. 6. cap. 12. pag.</hi> 339. diſtaſting and deteſting the flaughing Poems of <hi>Hermoditus,</hi> becauſe he would have made him (as they ſome Gnatoniſts, <hi>Alexander</hi>) the ſonne of Jupiter, and <hi>ſi quid mea carmina poſſunt:</hi> if I might be held wiſe or worthy enough to cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:161846:5"/>
our Mendatious and malignant <hi>Mercuries</hi> mixt with ſaturnall ſpirits, which caſt aſperſions on our ſtate Ephoriſts and Patriots as blacke as their inck, or that which the fiſh <hi>Scilopendra</hi> vomits out to blunder oft, and to trouble cleane waters; and theſe Court holy waters more poyſonous then thoſe of the Stygian lake, which they ſprinkle upon a Princely Monarchy, to doe after the Perſian Law, <hi>quod libet, licet,</hi> every thing, or any thing, without being queſtioned, Pope like, with <hi>cur ita facis,</hi> why doth it ſo? or without ſuch rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to counſell and counſellours (as the beſt <hi>temperamentum ad Pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> in the body Politicke) as the hot Hart (an emblem of regality) hath reference to the bellows of the lungs to blow upon it, and to coole it: I ſay, I would have all ſuch Mercurialized guilded paper poyſons, meerly conſumed by Tobacco pipes, like Tobacco, to ſmoke, or like the flattering Courtier <hi>Thurinus</hi> by ſmoake, as meerly conſecrated to <hi>Vulcan;</hi> or in the beſt uſe, if reprieved: I would have them imployed by ſome Chandelours to ſtop Muſtard-pots; or by Monſier <hi>A-jaix,</hi> as <hi>Harringtons</hi> Satyrs have metamorphized him.</p>
            <p>Withall I further expoſtulate with my mercenary Mercury, or Mounſier <hi>Mendax,</hi> why he, or any of his fraternity, was ſo long from the 10, 11, and 12, to the 17, 18, 19 of April in weaving a poor ſpiders web or Arachnees clew out of their owne invenomed bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ells, to catch poore credulous plebeian fleſh fleas; or rather in hat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of a wind egge or two, which by the incubation of ſome Toads, as poyſonous as themſelves, may bring forth Cockatrices; <hi>egregiam certe laudem &amp; ſpolia ampla tuliſti,</hi> every one of you have ſtoutly lyed and vied for the whet-ſtone: and after ſome pumping of your hide-bound genius, with <hi>Juno Lucina fer opem, perturiunt montes, naſcitur riduculus mus,</hi> you have brought forth a mouſe to get into the Trunkes of Alephants, or rather a blacke Rat to gnaw all Parliamentary papers and edicts; yet I propheſie, that if you bee once catcht out of your lurking holes, and <hi>Cacus</hi> dens, where you ſecurely croake (as all Schiſmaticall frogs) in corners, we have ſtate ſtorkes would catch you by the crags, and Lionized Cats, would clapper-claw you till you ſqueaked; and perhaps you may at laſt finde by wofull experience, that you may ſigh or ſing <hi>Ovids</hi> Elegiackes, with <hi>ingenio perii;</hi> your owne wits may be your owne woes, as <hi>Cambiſes</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> were ſlaine with their own ſwords; as <hi>Adonijah</hi> ſpoke words, and a Lieutenant of the Tower write lines, like <hi>Vrias</hi> his letters, to their owne deaths; ſo your owne pennes (with <hi>propriis configimur pennis</hi>) with which you pricke and pierce
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:161846:5"/>
our Senatours, as with the ſharpened quills of Porcupines, may pierce your ſelves; as its noted that <hi>Caſſius</hi> and <hi>Brutus,</hi> killed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with thoſe very ſwords which they drew againſt <hi>Caeſar;</hi> it may be you may know what it is to pulLions by the beard; you may buy repentance as dear by your abuſed wickedwits ſpurted (as mad dogs their ſlavers, as inraged Boares their froth, and horſes their foams) in the very faces of diſgraced Grandees; as <hi>Antiphon</hi> bought his bold jeaſt broken upon <hi>Dioniſius</hi> which coſt him his head; or as <hi>Anaxarchus</hi> bought his ſarciſmes caſt upon <hi>Anacreon,</hi> which afterwards brayed him in a mortar; as <hi>Pantaleon</hi> was caſt into a darke cave, and fed with the bread of affliction to his dying day for his baſe aſperſions caſt upon <hi>Arſinoe</hi> the wife of <hi>Liſimachus.</hi> No leſſe tragicall were the Iromes which ſome of the Nobles of <hi>Arragon</hi> ſpurted on <hi>Ranimirus</hi> their King, recalled out of a Monaſtery, which coſt no leſſe then e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leven of them their lives, with this caveat, <hi>ignor at vulpecula, cum quo ludat,</hi> the Fox knowes not with whom he playes when he is too bold with the Lion, as the tongue tragedies of theſe and many moe, you may ſee writ in their owne blood (as yours may be in time) if you have either will to read them, or skill to underſtand them, largely hiſtorified by <hi>Collenutius</hi> in his firſt booke of the Hiſtory of <hi>Naples</hi> p. 20. by <hi>Hagaceus</hi> in his Bohemian Chronicle, <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 171. by <hi>Strigellius</hi> upon <hi>Juſtin.</hi> pag. 169. by <hi>Woffius</hi> in his memorables <hi>Tom.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 359. chiefly by <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in his Apothegmes in his ſixt booke, <hi>fol.</hi> 478, 479. <hi>ſc.</hi> 548, 549, and in his 7 booke <hi>fol.</hi> 633. to all whom their owne licentious and ſcurrilous wits, unguided like <hi>Belliro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> horſes, without the <hi>Minervaes</hi> bridle of wiſdome, were as fatall and tragicall, as the horſe of <hi>Sejanus</hi> was to <hi>Caſſius</hi> and <hi>Tolobella,</hi> and to every one of his Maſters, and the Tholous gold to every one that poſſeſſed and plundered it, in whoſe broken glaſſes you may ſee ſo far your owne faces; that as generous ſpirits (like <hi>Alexander</hi> in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doning King <hi>Porus,</hi> and in killing audacious <hi>Clitus</hi> and too bold <hi>Caliſthenes</hi>) are alwayes more exaſperated with words then with ſwords, and will rather pardon Targets againſt them then tongues; ſo you may at laſt come to buy your impetuous ſcurrility in your <hi>ſcandalum magnatum</hi> in the higheſt degree, as dear as <hi>Semei</hi> his reviling of <hi>David,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. as <hi>Ra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſhekah</hi> his railings againſt <hi>Ezekias,</hi> 2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 19. as <hi>Michol</hi> her mockings of her royall husband, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 6. as <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Hagar</hi> their prophane ſcoffes againſt <hi>Iſaac<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Gen.</hi> 21. yea as copious as I have heard his invectives againſt a Platonicall <hi>Rex pacificus,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venged by an Engliſh <hi>Heroes;</hi> or as thoſe brats of Bethlehem
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:161846:6"/>
brought their hereditary ſcurrilous taunts againſt that Round<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, ſound-head <hi>Eliſha,</hi> torne (as their tongues had torne him) by She-bears in a juſt retaliated vengeance, 2 <hi>King.</hi> 2. ſuch Curs as you bawling ſo long againſt Lions, and ſuch Crowes as you, chatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſo long againſt incenſed Eagles, that they may lacerate and teare you as <hi>Hercules</hi> did <hi>Ops,</hi> ſince <hi>patientia lae ſa furor,</hi> the moſt noble and maſculine patience abuſed turnes into rage, as ſweet wine into ſowre vinegar; even a patient <hi>Abner</hi> too far provoked beyond his temper may ſmite with his ſharpe ſpeare a ſcurrilous <hi>Hazael,</hi> whoſe looſe tongue runs ſwifter then his heeles, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 23. and for your parts, were you knowne, I am perſwaded as you ſpeake and write what you will, you ſhould ſuffer what you would not, <hi>nemeſis a Tergo,</hi> a juſt revenge, dogs and haunts your unjuſt railing, like <hi>Brutus</hi> his ghoſt, you have a <hi>Cerberus</hi> that barkes within you, called conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, if it be not ſeared and cauterized, that <hi>multa miſer timeo, quia ſeri multa proterve.</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Needs muſt I feare to ſuffer much ere long,</l>
               <l>Since againſt earthly Gods rag'd hath my tongue.</l>
               <l>I have brought on me earth, and Heavens ire,</l>
               <l>By my inflamed tongue, with hels hot fire.</l>
               <l>In <hi>Phlegeton</hi> my tongue muſt feele moſt flames,</l>
               <l>Becauſe it here hath ſcortcht moſt noble names.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <head>Poena culpa proportionata.</head>
               <l>My puniſhment ſhall anſwer my demerit,</l>
               <l>When I belch out my Lucianized ſpirit.</l>
               <l>Since againſt Chriſt, and all his Saints I fought,</l>
               <l>My wage muſt ſuit the worke that I have wrought.</l>
               <l>As I have acted parts of <hi>Porphi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ie,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And <hi>Julian,</hi> their hell ſtill gapes for me.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>In the meane ſpace, <hi>quod defertur non aufertur, adeſt Rammiſia nemeſis, Thy tongue deviſeth miſchiefe like a ſharpe raizour, working deceitfully; Thou loveſt evill more then good, and lying rather then to ſpeake rightcouſneſſe; Thou loveſt all deceiving words, Oh thou deceitfull tongue, God ſhall likewiſe for ever deſtroy thee, he ſhall take thee away and plucke thee out of thy dwelling houſe, and out of the land of the living; the righteous alſo ſhall ſee and feare, and laugh at thee,</hi> Pſal. 52, 53. 4, 5, 6. The verdict is paſt, the decree thou ſeeſt is gone out like the decrees of the Medes and Perſians from the up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per houſe of Heaven, how ere thou ſleight, villifie and nullifie this lower houſe on earth, where God is terrible in the aſſembly of his Saints, both in the Senate and the Synod: but thou ſaieſt, <hi>quid
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:161846:6"/>
haec ad rom bum,</hi> what is this to ſlie Mercury, thou ſcofeſt them as <hi>bruta fulmina,</hi> ſquibs and fire-workes, lightning and thunder, without bolts, and ſleights the decrees of God, as much as of our terreſtriall Gods, yea, as over ſhooes, over boots, adding thirſt to drunkenneſſe, the <hi>Cain</hi>-like defence of the ſinne to the offence, thou with a brazen brow pleads <hi>recte fecisti;</hi> like <hi>Saul,</hi> that thou haſt ſaid and done all well, I <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. though <hi>mors in olla,</hi> death be in the inke pot, &amp; <hi>in penna Gehenna,</hi> hell be in the pen (as in the <hi>ſanguinnolent</hi> letters once of <hi>Ahab</hi> and <hi>Jezabel</hi> againſt <hi>Naboth,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21. 6. of the Scribes and Phariſees againſt the primative Saints, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 2, 3. of that accurſed Court Commet <hi>Hamman,</hi> againſt the Jewes, <hi>Hester</hi> 6. and (as ſome ſay, <hi>aut mentiuntur poëtae</hi>) out of the Engliſh Court Frenchified into Ireland, dyed red with the blood of a <hi>C.</hi> and ſo thouſand Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants) yet Matchiavillian Mercury like <hi>Solomons</hi> Harlot wipes his mouth, and ſaith, he hath not ſinned; he preſents like ſome Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardens once <hi>omnia bene</hi> all is wel on his part, he finds an <hi>ignoramus</hi> in himſelf of any delinquency againſt the Parliament, he is not looſe i'th faſt, he will ſtand ſtifly to his tackling, and like <hi>Tom</hi> tell troth, juſtifie what he hath ſaid, as a plaine Macedonian, calling a ſpaid, a ſpaid; he is not bird-mouthed, he will ſay more; but to ſtop his mouth with this bone to gnaw on, or choake-peare, and to cope up this Beare with this muzzle: how is it then, that like the Perſians and our wilde vilde Iriſh, he throwes his poyſoned darts and runnes away? how is it that after crowing before the victory, this Craven flyes the pit (as the French coward once in a duell from the Iriſh Courſey) ere ever ſtroke be given? how is it that he playes leaſt in ſight, walkes by owl-light, and keeps hearts in <hi>Tenebris?</hi> how is it that like a wag-taile, a Scarabaean flea, or a Gentleman in debt, he skips here and there, as a ſquirrill in a tree, we know not how to ſeize on him; nay as though he had <hi>Gyges</hi> his ring, walking invi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly? how is it that we cannot finde him? how is it that he dare not father his baſtard-lyes, of which his corrupt heart was the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, his tongue the midwife, and the wicked world (now foſtering all villany) the nurſe; ſure truth ſeeks no corners: And if <hi>Mercury</hi> reply that I am an Anomiſt as well as he, and ſo retort upon me <hi>medice cura teipſum,</hi> to cure my ſelfe in what I thinke him diſeaſed; I tell him <hi>impar congreſſus;</hi> there is not the like caſe nor cauſe: for firſt, its probable I am knowne, or may be <hi>ex conſequenti,</hi> as <hi>Hercules</hi> his proportion by his foot, and the Lion by his paw, ſo far as I can ſcarce be concealed, if I would live, lurke, and ſleep in a warme skin. Secondly, why ſhould I reveale my ſelfe to an Antagoniſt? I
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:161846:7"/>
know not againſt whoſe imaginary perſon to fight, I ſhould but beat the air, ſow the wind, and reap the whirlewind: but let Mr. <hi>Mercury</hi> be <hi>Mercury</hi> ſublimating, or-<hi>Mercurius ſublimus,</hi> hold up his head like a man; <hi>ſub dio, ſub jove f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igus,</hi> let him not as the woodcocke from the fouler, or the Aſſe from the Woolfe, hide his head in a buſh; or as the Panther hides his horrid head from the leſſer beaſts till he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure them, ſhewing them onely his ſpeckled, and ſpotted body, and then I will ſo ſhew my ſelfe in diſplayed colours, that we will runne at Tilt, till I hope to unhorſe him, though perhaps I ſhall never un-Aſſe him, making himſelfe here a wicked witty foole in Print, a meer <hi>As in preſenti,</hi> that to pleaſe his Malignant maſters, he may have <hi>As in futuro,</hi> ſo many yellow duſted ſtuds, as may trap him, like <hi>Apulejus</hi> his golden Aſſe, being as yet but meere <hi>Eu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nanus</hi> his Aſſe, faining to roare in a Lions skin, or a ſympathizing foale of <hi>Balaams</hi> Aſſe boldly kicking both at Prophets and Patritians, to kick both out of Eccleſiaſticall and ſecular ſeats.</p>
            <p>But I have curried this Aſſe enough with my toothed pen in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſatirizings, onely to make him as humble as that Aſſe who onely of irrationalls carried Chriſt (as Saint <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> and his Virgin mother of rationalls) being for the preſent as proud in his imaginary carrying of Regality on his backe to <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> as that Aſſe was in the Poet, which carried the goddeſſe <hi>Iſis;</hi> or that Mule in the French <hi>Stevens</hi> Apology, who being borrowed of a Lady, to carry a Pope, would never ſuffer any to beſtride her after, but the Pope, as though ſhe had been a <hi>Beucephalus,</hi> and her carriage an <hi>Alexander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But let us heare the Mercurialized Aſſe (in his owne conceit, <hi>tanquam Aſinus ad Liram,</hi> or <hi>Aſinus ad Tribunall</hi>) brey in his owne dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, as farre from the wit of a true Mercury indeed, <hi>Nuncius deorum<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> who charmed <hi>Argus,</hi> or of <hi>Mercurius Triſmegiſtus,</hi> who was the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gifer of the <hi>Aegrohans,</hi> as <hi>Thirſites</hi> is farre from the wit of an <hi>Vliſſes,</hi> or wiſdome of <hi>Neſtor,</hi> or <hi>Bavius</hi> and <hi>Mevius</hi> from the ſweet numbers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> of <hi>Virgil</hi> and <hi>Ovid;</hi> but liſten how he begins, as the Iriſh, with an<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>O hone, like a</hi> Bittern <hi>and dying</hi> Hena.</p>
            <p>With a groane, <hi>O,</hi> he cryes, <hi>Sicke, ſicke, ſicke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas! whats the matter? ſome Gallieniſt or Paracelſian ſoone to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> caſt his water, or ſome <hi>Jupiter menecrates</hi> to ſave himſelfe, we loſe a moſt pretious <hi>don quipot,</hi> whoſe wits ſparkle like ſalt in the fire, and make ſuch paſtime-paſſing meaſure, as there needs no other foole nor fidler where he comes: But whats his ſickneſſe, ſure he hath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:161846:7"/>
tooke no ſurfet, like his Idolized Prelates of ſlit noſes and cropt eares, whoſe heads have beene ever ſince wrapt with rent rotchets; nor is he pain'd with the ſtone in his Pharoized heart, for that as white powder and ſulfuration kills without noiſe; but its probable by his hot mouth and his furd tongue that had need be ſcaped by ſome Skinner, it is ſo foule, that his blood is wonderouſly diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered in the burning feavor of ſome raging luſt: I ſee by his colour he is troubled with a very bad liver, and I ſmell by the vapours of his ſtinking breath, blaſting even pure white paper, much more Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutians, that he hath very rotten lungs; and without queſtion he is much troubled with the ſpleene, that Epidemicall diſeaſe ſpreads further then any plague amongſt all his fellows, from all parts of the land, running as frenzie and Popery in a blood, as an hereditary diſeaſe amongſt them; or it may be this <hi>Bacchanalean,</hi> is top or tap heavy, he hath wanted ſleepe ſo long, that he begins to rave or talke idly, he had need have ſome poppy, <hi>opium,</hi> or dormitory drug, or Hellibore to reſtore him to his right wits.</p>
            <p>Oh, but he is ſicker then he was, call in neighbours, hold up his head, he begins to perbreake his minde in a dog-ſicke drunken vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit, a beſome and a bowle preſently, or a Scavinger, up with it man, if it be but a gallon it will eaſe thy ſtomach; I doubt he will diſgorge his very gal, there comes matter from him as black as ink, as poyſonous as <hi>Sodomes</hi> lake, which infects the fiſh thrown in it, and the birds which flye over it. The onely way to cure him throughly now, that he caſts naturally, and as phyſically as any hawke (ſince he ſtill raves) is to phlebotomize him in his vaine veynes, and to make an inciſion into his ſcull (perhaps there may flye out<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>dotte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rils, widgyns, and woodcockes, and to take out his braines and well waſht with holy water, and ſtopt like a calves head with ſalt and ſage, ſo ſtitch it up againe with ſome ſollid counſel, hee may come to be as ſound both in body and braine, as the eight wiſe men, or a gull of <hi>Gotham,</hi> capable to be vicar of all fooles, chiefly if he be dieted daily with Rew, and Thriſis and True love, and Hearts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, and All heale, <hi>alias</hi> patience, and rub'd over a while with <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guentum baccalinum,</hi> or Crab-tree oyle in Bedlam, or Bridewell, hee may yet live many a faire day, to come to the office of Mr. of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels or Rebels, or Lord of miſ-rule: but he is not onely ſick him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, as I gather by his groaning O: and by the ſymptomes of his diſeaſes, dropt even from his polluted penne, but as though this Mountebanke quackſalver, or ſome of his fellow Empericks, pitied
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:161846:8"/>
them, or could preſcribe their cure, he tels us that the Saints are ſicke, and he diſturbs their diſtempers with more diſtemper in himſelfe (as <hi>Diogenes</hi> once trampled <hi>Platoes</hi> pride with his dirty feet in greater pride) that the Saints are ſicke I marvell not, yea ſicke to the very heart, mourning like Doves in the deſert, and Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans in the wilderneſſe, yea waſhing their very couches with tears, and their beds with weeping, for their owne ſinnes, and the ſinnes and ſufferings of the times, as did <hi>David, Hezekias, Lot, Jeremy, Ezra, Nehemiah,</hi> and other holy mourners in Sion, in their dayes, <hi>Pſal. 6. Pſal. 38. Pſal. 51. 2 King. 20. Eſay 38. 2 Pet. 2. Nehem. 1. Ezra 10. Jer.</hi> 9. 1. as indeed they have now more cauſe then ever to be ſoule-ſicke, and to weepe ſtreames of blood for the ſlaine of the people both corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>really and ſpiritually; to ſee ſtill the diſtempers of theſe unjoynted cuperate, bleeding, if not laſt breathing, Antipodized times, in which the whole head is ſicke in the body Politicall, and the heart heavy; yea from the crowne of the head, to the ſole of the foot, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but wounds, blaines and putrifactions, <hi>Eſa</hi> 1. 6. and likely to mend (like winter waies, ſoure Ale in ſummer, roten apples, and old gangreen ulcers) ſtill worſe and worſe, chiefly when the State Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitians are obſtructed in their cures by ſuch raſh and rude Empericks as himſelfe, who all infected as with the Kings evill, from <hi>Dan</hi> to <hi>Beerſhebah,</hi> would ſo cure Church and State, by reducing againe Papized, Diotrephian, domineering Epiſcopacie, without any mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification, as by proſecuting <hi>in ſtatu quo prius,</hi> Altar bowing, and turning all Religion like<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> bottle Ale into frothy Ceremonies, drawing in ſo, perverted Popery by Hiſpaniolized and Frenchified ſtratagems, as by head and ſhoulders (as <hi>Talus</hi> beaſts into his den) by bringing upon us downright Popery, to the probable more then Pariſian Calabrian, Merindolian, and Queen <hi>Maries</hi> Maſſe maſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cring of our bodies, to the loſſe of Religion, the life of our ſoules, by a conflagration, and a Phaetonian confuſion of all; he and his Parliamentary antagoniſts, would ſo bring us peace with loſſe of grace: as the ſonnes of <hi>Brutus</hi> brought peace to themſelves and <hi>Rome,</hi> in ſweating to bring in the banniſhed Taraquins; or as the Duke <hi>de Alva,</hi> that Storke amongſt Belgicke frogs, brought peace to the Netherlands, in labouring with Cardinall <hi>Greenvill</hi> to plant (with Biſhops) the Spaniſh Inquiſition; or as the Macedonian <hi>Phillip,</hi> proffered peace to the Athenians upon the delivery of their City <hi>Atlas,</hi> (the Speaker in their Parliament) <hi>Demoſthenes;</hi> which was as he told them, parallel to the Wolves, who would ſweare
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:161846:8"/>
peace and truce with the Shepherds, upon condition they would hang up all their dogs, the keepers of them, and of their flockes. Alas poor Quackſalvers, you knew much the true cauſe of our war, or cauſe or cure for grace and peace, as if you ſhould cure an ulce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous rankling wound with oyles of mace or vitruo, without cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting out the poyſoned bullet: you are ſo drunke with wine and wrath, or prejudicate opinion, as Crowes with vomiting nuts, that you diſcerne of things that differ, as blinde men of colours, yea be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt tranſcendent regality, and legality (keeping it Sea-like with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in its bounds and limits) as <hi>Midas</hi> with his Aſſes eares, betwixt <hi>Pans</hi> harſh and untuned pipe, and <hi>Apolloes</hi> harmonious lute. This mentall madneſſe, and intoxication of French Philters makes Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury ſmile (to give you his Rhymes without reaſon) to ſee our Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours curſed plots ſhould want ſucceſſe, and leave them ſots; in which to give him a <hi>Rowland</hi> for his <hi>Oliver,</hi> and to pen prick this windy bladder, or watery bubble, leſt he ſwell too big, even till he burſt like the fabled frog.</p>
            <lg>
               <l>WHat a Simplician, what a Sot,</l>
               <l>Have I to grapple with, God wot?</l>
               <l>By what inventions, wiles, and ſtraines,</l>
               <l>Shall I beat wit into his braines?</l>
               <l>With what <hi>Collirium Celidine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall I rub, ſcrub his dazled eyne?</l>
               <l>Where ſhall I beg, or buy in ſadneſſe,</l>
               <l>Right Hellibore to cure this madneſſe.</l>
               <l>Of this unworm'd, mouth-foaming Cur,</l>
               <l>Who foiſts, and keeps a ſtinking ſtur.</l>
               <l>As <hi>Cerberus</hi> his fierceſt whelpe,</l>
               <l>Who againſt Sun and Moone doth yelpe;</l>
               <l>Our Plannets, and our fixed Stars,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Centaures</hi> bold, once manag'd Wars</l>
               <l>'Gainſt Heaven: and <hi>Pelion</hi> piled high</l>
               <l>On <hi>Oſſa,</hi> for to ſcale the skie:</l>
               <l>How this mad head, malignant heart</l>
               <l>Re-acts againe, each furious part</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Ajax, Hercules</hi> inraged,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Bajazet</hi> in irons caged:</l>
               <l>Who like that demonaick <hi>Saul</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Juſt <hi>Jonathans</hi> would naile toth' wall;</l>
               <l>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:161846:9"/>Our <hi>Davids,</hi> our ſage Senators kill,</l>
               <l>And ſtab with his Gooſe (poyſoned) quill;</l>
               <l>That to a Piſtoll turnes his pen</l>
               <l>To ſhoot to death out Statiz'd men.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Cyclopſt,</hi> like blinde <hi>Polipheme,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Uliſſes</hi> doth no more eſteeme,</l>
               <l>Then a Phlebeian <hi>Corrydon,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Who woolfe-like would gnaw on his bone:</l>
               <l>What Orphean lire, can charme brute blocks,</l>
               <l>More then wilde Tygers <hi>Panthers</hi> foxe:</l>
               <l>When they a quarrell meane to picke,</l>
               <l>Both ſheep and ſhepheards blood to licke:</l>
               <l>For who, but an incarnate devill,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> villany train'd and fleſht in evill,</l>
               <l>Like <hi>Jaques Clement, Ravillack,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Faux Lopus,</hi> worſt of all the packe,</l>
               <l>Of Papiz'd Serpents, ſubtle ſnakes,</l>
               <l>Freſh ſpawned from the ſtigian lakes,</l>
               <l>Would make ſuch dire and damn'd conſtructions,</l>
               <l>That they ſhould be the States deſtructions,</l>
               <l>Who are State <hi>Decians, Phocions,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Horatians, Scipioes, Fabians;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Yea the Kings friends, and in their wars</l>
               <l>Foes to his <hi>Gaveſtons, Hammans, Cars;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With all props to our Churches vines</l>
               <l>For falling, rotting, it declines</l>
               <l>To dregs of Papall ſuperſtition,</l>
               <l>The worſt of any vines condition;</l>
               <l>To call ſuch Catoes, Catelines,</l>
               <l>Hanniballs, our Hectors in baſe lines;</l>
               <l>Heretiques, and Schiſmaticks, our Divines,</l>
               <l>Orthodox in Sinod, or dry vines;</l>
               <l>Our Patriots, Pirates, Pilates, Traitors,</l>
               <l>Tymous miſanthropiſts, Prince-haters;</l>
               <l>Our ſtrongeſt Pillers, Caterpillers,</l>
               <l>Canniballs, aſſidates, blood-ſpillers</l>
               <l>Our peace projectors, and protectors,</l>
               <l>Delinquents, Cenſors, and Correctors:</l>
               <l>Who but knowne knaves, Dulmans proud ſots,</l>
               <l>Would ſtigmatize, all theſe for plots.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:161846:9"/>But I leave deſcanting in Verſe, to plaine proſe, like plain dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, (Poets being the beſt of writers, except Orators in proſe, by Sir <hi>Henry Savils</hi> cenſure;) only I take notice of his jeare, <hi>riſi ſucceſſupoſſe carere dolos,</hi> that their plots, as he blaſphemes their politicall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings ſhould want ſucceſſe; ſo had they beene ſucceſſefull hee had hugg'd them, as <hi>doli boni, &amp; pia fraudes,</hi> very legall plots in his owne phraiſe: blinde buzzard, that meaſures the regularity or ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>regularity of an action by the ſucceſſe: ſo no doubt this Simplician had applauded the powder Treaſon, had it ſucceeded as much as Pope <hi>ſextus</hi> the aſſaſſinating of the French King, or <hi>Mariana</hi> the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſian maſſacre, or <hi>Cardan</hi> his <hi>Nero,</hi> and <hi>Cateline,</hi> or ſome the Sicilian evening ſong, in butchering the French, and <hi>Yorkes</hi> betraying of <hi>Devontree; Sinon</hi> of <hi>Troy, Zopirus</hi> of <hi>Babylon,</hi> Pope <hi>Clemens</hi> and the French Kings ruinating of the <hi>Templers,</hi> (as ſome Carnaliſts now juſtifie, the barbarous cruelties, and Canniballized inhumanities of the Iriſh wolves, lately devouring our Engliſh Proteſtants) be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of their good ſucceſſe: O Paſquill Mad-caps, and giddy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed Ganders, to meaſure actions fame-worthy in their owne nature, to be blame-worthy becauſe of bad ſucceſſe; blame the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of the word then, becauſe it is to ſome the ſavor of death, as it was to <hi>Herod, Judas, Pharaoh,</hi> the unbeleeving Jewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles; blame the Sunne, becauſe it hardens the clay, cauſeth weeds and tares to grow as well as fruits and corne, and makes dunghils to ſtinke; blame good ſeed, becauſe falling into ſtony and thorny ground, it brings forth no fruit; blame a skilfull Phyſitian, and his beſt phyſicke, becauſe it alwayes workes not wiſhed effects in ſome impatient patients, which effects muſt come from God, as we may ſee in the caſes of <hi>Hezekias</hi> and <hi>Aſa,</hi> 2 <hi>Chr.</hi> 16. 2 <hi>King.</hi> 20. for <hi>non eſt in medico ſemper relevetur ut aeger,</hi> bad cauſes oft producing good effects, as <hi>ex malis moribus bonae leges,</hi> good lawes proceeding from bad manners; as pearles, its ſaid, are got in the heads of ſome Serpents, yea Antidotes againſt poyſons, even from poyſonous ſnakes and newtes: And the Redemption of the world, by divine providence helpt forward by <hi>Judas</hi> his treachery, and the Jews cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. 27, 28. as the Lord gets glory in Juſtice or Mercy, in pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing or pardoning, even from the ſinnes of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 20. ſo on the contrary, good cauſes oft produce bad effects: as zealous prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, like a good mother, produced bad daughters, in the undeſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved impriſoning of <hi>Paul, Silas, Jeremy,</hi> the beheading of <hi>John Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt,</hi> the burning of <hi>Hierome</hi> of <hi>Prague, John Huſſe, Savinoriola,</hi> our <hi>Lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer,</hi> it coſting him his hearts blood, as he oft propheſied it would.
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:161846:10"/>
Oh the madneſſe not only of this many headed beaſt the multitude, but of all other Brutized Carnaliſts, Moraliſts, Newters, papized, and ill-affected of all ſorts, who bellow againſt the Parliament, and gore them in the ſides, and toſſe them as mad Bulls of Baſan, on the hornes of their powers, becauſe their devoures and indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours as yet want wiſhed and expected ſucceſſe; having eyes as quick as <hi>Linceus,</hi> or the Serpent <hi>Epidaurus</hi> to look at their reall or imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry failings perhaps as men (they being neither Gods nor Angels, but men, ſubject to errors like <hi>Moſes, Aaron, David, Solomon,</hi> &amp; the reſt, the beſt) and like Cocatrices and Baſilisks, poyſoning what they ſpy in their Heteroclite ſucceſſes: but being blind as moles in deſcerning what God hath done by them already (eaten bread being forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten) in ſecuring the Kingdome from forreigne invaſion, in remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving or obſtructing Achitophellized counſellours and counſells from the King, in preventing that maſſacre which was plotted for <hi>England,</hi> as well as <hi>Ireland,</hi> by Cardinall <hi>Barbarino Cimeus,</hi> the Popes Nuntio, and other <hi>ſanguinnolent</hi> agents here, diſcovered in Mr. <hi>Pryns Romes</hi> Maſter-piece, by ſecuring every mans propriety from a <hi>ſic vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo, ſic jubeo, Dominus opus habet,</hi> chiefly from an overflowing and innundation of Popery, as it broke in upon us in many opened ſluces unſtopped, but dayly made wider, as any may ſee that is not purblinde, or ſhuts not his eyes againſt the Sunne.</p>
            <p>And what though as is pretended, and as this Iſmalitiſh Mercury ſcoffes, that the Parliament hath an Army of Sectaries, though the Husbandmen perhaps were too ſupine, whilſt theſe tares were ſown by Jeſuits unſuſpected, undetected, camelionized into pretended Tradeſmen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Souldiers, Enthuſiaſtically inſpired, as Lay plebeian preachers; yet theſe Sectaries are not ſo ſtrongly radicated as Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, nor ſo <hi>ſanguinnolent,</hi> and State-firing, nor ſo difficult to bee ſuppreſſed, being but like their primitive predeceſſors in all ages, <hi>nubiculae cito tranſenutes,</hi> cloud which will ſoon be blown over, felt we but once the Favonian winds and gales of a gracious-peace, beſides theſe Sects are not to bee aſcribed to the Parliament more then <hi>Goodwins</hi> ſands to <hi>Steutertons</hi> ſteeple, they being but as ill humours to be purged out, or as Kibes, Carbuncles, Botches, glaſſie eyes, and wooden legs in the body; no part of the body Politicall or Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall; and ſuppoſe they be too glutinous and viſcous, as yet to be purged, yea that the ſons of <hi>Zerviah</hi> be as yet too ſtrong for thoſe of the houſe of <hi>David, Zach.</hi> 12. 10. yea ſuppoſe to ſpeake myſtically that <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> his young boy ſhould by degrees and gradations,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:161846:10"/>
ſway too much in <hi>Athens;</hi> yet our Parliamenteires are to be pitied as paſſives, not ſcoffed as actives, if in any thing expoſing them to the ſtars or ſpits of conſtruction, they be as ſome in a Coach carried or hurried, not in their owne naturall, but in a more coactive mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as in ſome caſes (as I have found experimentally in my ſelfe and others) and as many can give the <hi>probatum eſt,</hi> a man as <hi>David</hi> once, yea a conglobed ſociety may be in ſuch ſtreights, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24. 14 ſailing as it were betwixt the <hi>Scylla</hi> of ſome inconveniencies, &amp; the <hi>Caribdis</hi> of ſome miſchiefes, that doe what he can with the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all his beſt powers and parts, he ſhall ſplit upon one or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with ſome ſhipwracke, will he, nill he; like to him in the Fable, who held a wolfe by the eares, who if he held him longer would be ſure to bite him, yet if he let him goe, he would worry; and is it not with State Phyſitians thinke we, as with corporeall? the patient may be in ſuch a poſture by contrary diſeaſes, ſome from hot, ſome from cold cauſes, that their beſt skill and will knowes not ſo to cure one, but they muſt to their griefe, and non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pluſſing of Phyſicke increaſe the other, the ſalve being oft as ill or worſe then the ſore; and the medicine more pretious then the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe, dangerous.</p>
            <p>But to trace this tripping Mercury further in his impudiating humor, he danceth without a piper, and cuts his croſſe capers &amp; Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valtoes, as though he had a Welch harp, or Scotch bag piper tuned in ſuch Martiall ſtreyns as his heart could wiſh; our preſent frets be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his mentall muſicke, he playes as a Porpoyce and a Dolphin, in our ſuppoſed ſtormes, and makes himſelfe merry (with that which makes every gracious heart ſorry) with the City murmuring, the Apprentices mutining, the Scots voting the Parliament Covenant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crackers, falſe, fraudulent, every one curſing them, ready to cut their throats, the Weſt and <hi>Wales,</hi> and all againſt them; and this is his ſandy and unglewed argument that therefore their cauſe is nought: he might as well have concluded as much againſt <hi>Elias</hi> when <hi>Ahab, Jezabel,</hi> the Prieſts of <hi>Baall,</hi> all <hi>Iſrael</hi> bowing to <hi>Baal,</hi> he thought himſelfe Bird alone, not one to ſtand for him, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 9. 14 and againſt <hi>Jeremy</hi> when the <hi>Fedifragous</hi> King, the fluctuate people, the perfideous Elders, the Prelaticall <hi>Paſhur,</hi> and all were againſt him, except one Blackamore, and he ſaw nothing but pikes, perils, impriſonments, death and danger; all being ſo adulterous and treacherous againſt him, that he wiſht for a wilderneſſe to lurke from them, <hi>Jer.</hi> 9. 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 20. 2. &amp; 9. 10. and againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:161846:11"/>
againſt whom the people ſo oft murmured, and were ſo ſore incenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that they tooke up ſtones to ſtone them, <hi>Exod.</hi> 15. 24. <hi>cap.</hi> 16. 2. 3. <hi>Num.</hi> 20 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 21 5. <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. 41, 42. but chiefly againſt <hi>David,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom as the triall of his faith, fortitude, patience and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance on God, ere God ſettled him in his promiſed Kingdom, that he might firſt crowne his ſufferings (as he did <hi>Jobs</hi> patience, and <hi>Pauls</hi> perſeverance, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 7, 8. and make him exemplary to all imployed by God in great workes, for his glory, and the good of a people) hee ſet not onely <hi>Saul</hi> againſt him to hunt him as a Partridge, but the <hi>Zephins, Achitophel, Doeg</hi> and his owne wife <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choll</hi> to mocke him, and <hi>Shemei</hi> to revile him, yea the very people to ſtone him, being oft in ſuch ſtraights, (greater then our Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ever yet) that hee thought there was but a ſtep betwixt him and death, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20. 3. <hi>chap.</hi> 23. 16. <hi>chap.</hi> 24. 14. <hi>chap.</hi> 30. 6. Yea, might not this fellow have concluded as much againſt ſome of the <hi>German Henries,</hi> and <hi>Fredericks:</hi> fighting the Lords battailes, when one Antichriſtian Pope after another had excommunicated them, and armed their own Subjects againſt them: yet ſome of them for all this marvelouſly, and miraculouſly delivered, as were oft the <hi>Hugonites</hi> in <hi>France, Huniades</hi> in <hi>Hungare, Luther</hi> in <hi>Saxon,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> here in <hi>England,</hi> the late <hi>Polſgrave</hi> (called the King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemia</hi>) and millions more in Hiſtory, whom God preſerved and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved to better times, and to better ends and purpoſes, after he had pulled them as brands out of the fire, and brought them <hi>Daniel</hi>-like out of the very jaws of Lyons, and as his three couragious ſervants out of the very flaming furnace, where they were tried as pure gold, ere the Lord effected by them thoſe great workes of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or preſervation of a people, for which he fitted them by ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fiery trialls, and ſure if the Parliament ſtand for God, as he hath promiſed to ſtand for them, and to deliver them as all his true Members, Miniſters and Magiſtrates, out of all their troubles, and to honour them which honour him, <hi>Joſh,</hi> 1. 5. <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. 6. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 34. 18, 19. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 30. <hi>Act.</hi> 18. 10. <hi>Eſay</hi> 43. 1, 2, 3. Though all the cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated principalities and powers in earth and hell were againſt them, they muſt proſper and flouriſh: if their work be of men, I muſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the decree is againſt them, it will come to naught, <hi>Act.</hi> 5. 38<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the branches that are not in Chriſt wither, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15. 6. But if their work be of God it cannot be overthrown, <hi>Act.</hi> 5; 39. who fight againſt it fight againſt God, as glaſſe tilting againſt braſſe, to their breaking, as waves ſurging and bluſtering againſt a rock, daſhing themſelves
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:161846:11"/>
to froath and foame; <hi>omnes priminter divinitus,</hi> he that conſults with many Inſtances given by <hi>Melancton</hi> in his Poſtills, <hi>part,</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 553. and <hi>Strigellius</hi> on the Pſalmes, <hi>pag</hi> 66. in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. ſhall ſee Gods hand fearfully on thoſe who have had heads, hearts, or hands againſt his Church: as alſo other Inſtances given by the ſame Author, in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 41. <hi>pag.</hi> 334. in <hi>Hezekias, Conſtantine, Obediah, Abdemelech,</hi> the wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of <hi>Sarepta, John Frederick</hi> the Duke of <hi>Saxony;</hi> and I may adde our Engliſh late <hi>Deborah,</hi> our <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> with many moe, friends of the Church, in <hi>hac vita glorioſe ornati,</hi> ever gloriouſly honoured and patronized in this life, which I preſcribe as a cordiall and cooler to our Senators, againſt the hot tongue poyſon of this Mercurialized ſonne of <hi>Beliall,</hi> who being more perfect in his lying, then in his Latin-tongue, tells us of the brave exploits of two turn-coats in <hi>Wales, Poyer</hi> and <hi>Powell</hi> in three times defeating the forces ſent againſt them, though I have it from the mouth of a credible Colonell, that being but one 100. or 2000. ſent againſt them, have driven them into their Cony-burrowes, their Caſtles (ſtronger then <hi>Tyrones</hi> old Forts of bogs, woods and mountaines) but I ſee in moſt lying and flying newes, moſt ſpeake not as the truth is, but as they would tune it, as they are affected and infect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; but leaving this as triviall, that in which his <hi>ſerpentina quedam ſanies,</hi> his ſerpentine ſpirit ſhews it ſelf the moſt is; that as Sathans working tooles deſirous to caſt his <hi>Ataes</hi> ball, and <hi>Phaetonian</hi> flames betwixt the Scots and Parliament. This Bedlam blatters that they have voted them Covenant-crackers, falſe, and fraudulent in all their undertakings. A ſharpe fang'd Cur, indeed he bites deepe in taxation, if the clapper of his tongue were not looſe hung in his probation; venting but meerly like the eccho, an airy ſound, for it were better his tongue were cheeſe, and all the Cats in the Towne were nibling it, ere this were any truer then <hi>Aeſops</hi> fables, or <hi>Lucians</hi> Dialogues.</p>
            <p>I hope our Parliament hath more care of credit with man, and confidence with God, then to breake that Covenant which is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed and ſealed by oath before the great God of heaven, which even <hi>medea in euripides,</hi> calls <hi>Juramentorum cuſtos,</hi> the great Lord Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of oaths inviolable, moſt ſeverely alwayes puniſhing their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fringers; as any that will but conſult Hiſtorians, chiefly <hi>Honicer</hi> his Theater of examples, our D. <hi>Beard</hi> in his Theater of Gods judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and <hi>Paul</hi> of <hi>Hitzin</hi> in his Ethicks, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 18, 20. ſhall ſee the fearfull juſtice of Earth and Heaven, falling upon <hi>Zedekias</hi> break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:161846:12"/>
his ſworne fealty with <hi>Nabuchadnezzar,</hi> upon the Carthagini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, ſo oft in fringing their oaths with the Romans. One <hi>Hatto</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Mentz</hi> at laſt eaten with Rats, by perjury betraying <hi>Albert</hi> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Bamburg,</hi> to <hi>Lodovick</hi> the third Emperour chiefly, on <hi>Paches</hi> the Athenian Captaine, killing himſelfe after he had by a falſe oath murthered <hi>Hippias,</hi> and won his beſieged City. One <hi>Laudiſlaus</hi> King of <hi>Hungary</hi> and <hi>Poland,</hi> who the yeare 1614. by the counſell of Cardinall <hi>Julian</hi> breaking his ſworne truce with <hi>Amu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rath</hi> the Turke, brought him into Europe ſeverely to revenge it, with the loſſe of his life and Crowne; as alſo of the great Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian <hi>Phillip,</hi> who by the judgement of <hi>Pauſanias</hi> periſhed ſo miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably with all his blood, becauſe according to the proverb and practice of <hi>Liſander,</hi> he thought Peers and Princes were to be decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with oaths, as children with bables and toyes; but I hope I need preſcribe no ſalve, where as yet I finde no ſore.</p>
            <p>In his next morrice dance, this hobby-horſe neighes out prophane mirth, in the revolt of the Lord <hi>Inchequin</hi> from the Parliament, of whom I will onely interpoſe thus much:</p>
            <p>Firſt, that to give him his due, he hath done acts worthy of a brave Gentleman, a pretented Proteſtant, and a Martialiſt, becauſe to the Iriſh, ſo long as he was himſelf tuned in a right key, as <hi>Tanibut</hi> ſometimes was to the French, and <hi>Huniades,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt to the Turks, <hi>Terror malae gentis,</hi> a terror to his wicked natives; but <hi>finis coronat opus,</hi> what is it to begin well, as did <hi>Pauls</hi> Galathians, <hi>Judas</hi> the Diſciple, <hi>Demas Pauls</hi> follower, <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate, <hi>Nero</hi> in his <hi>quinquennium:</hi> the mutable <hi>Occebolius,</hi> and ſome Pernized weather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cocks in our dayes, and to end ill: to make ſhipwracke in the ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to give, like the Cow, a good meale of milke, and to throw it downe with her heeles; to weave and unweave a <hi>Penelopes</hi> web, ſince the end crownes every worke; and conſtancy next to conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is the grace of every great man, who would gaine and retaine the repute of a good man.</p>
            <p>Secondly, his revolt is more diſtaſtefull to ſuch judicious ones as have obſerved his poſtures as he was active or paſſive, in that hee was not (as <hi>vox populi,</hi> which is not ever <hi>vox veri,</hi> hath reported him) in any great wants or exigents in defects of monies, ever held the very nerves and ſinewes of War, ſince he received as much as any in the Kingdome, large ſummes from the Parliament, beſides his conſiderable contributions from the greateſt part of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince of <hi>Munſter;</hi> for I know the want of men, munition and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:161846:12"/>
hath oft much diſtracted and diſtreſſed many Heroyick ſpirits, and put them upon ſtrange exigents and inconveniencies, when their ſilver muſicke was too long in tuning, and made them all frets.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, I diſtaſte it the moſt, that he is joyned to the Rebells; but though I cannot ſay, as <hi>Noah</hi> of his ſonne, <hi>nec de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o melius putavi,</hi> that I never hoped better of him; for indeed, his flowry ſpring pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth yet a better harveſt then Popery: yet thus much I ſay, as I thought once of the great <hi>Ormond</hi> when he protected ſo many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells, to the no ſmall prejudice of the Proteſtants, and ſuffered ſome in Caſtles to flye out as Wood-cocks in a miſt, ſome officers who had them in a pinfold, being blinded with white and yellow duſt: So I have thought of <hi>Inchequin</hi> in ſome politicall reſpects, that at laſt <hi>tandem aliquando, Joſeph</hi> could not, would not forget his brethren, more then Queene <hi>Heſter</hi> could forget her people and kindred, <hi>Heſt.</hi> 8. 6. Nor more then a Catholicke Queene can for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get her Catholickes, not lying for nothing in the boſome of a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Prince. Yet notwithſtanding I perſwade my ſelfe he is ſo reſolute a Proteſtant, that <hi>Totman</hi> will not ſo far turne French, as that he will revolt to Papiſme; the grounds of my perſwaſion is this:</p>
            <p>1. Becauſe his veſſell was ſeaſoned with the truth in his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, therefore its hopefull to ſavour of the tincture, <hi>quo ſemel eſt imbutare.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, his converſion from Popery was not coactive, as whipt to it when he was a ward, as by a violent motion, <hi>non trabendo ſed du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendo,</hi> but by a worke of illumination upon him in hearing of Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, therefore more probable to be more ſincere and permanent, it being very obſervable, that thoſe that are haled and drawne to any Religion by force or feare, are like Cytteron ſtrings too high ſtretcht, to ſtand long in tune without breaking (as <hi>Sigebert</hi> in his Chronicles tells us of ſome Jewes inforced to be baptized in <hi>Leo Iſaurus</hi> the third his time, preſently waſht it off againe, and returned like judaizing dogs to their owne vomit, the like did ſome Jewes in <hi>Ratisbone</hi> in <hi>Henry</hi> the 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> time, <hi>anno dom.</hi> 1086. as <hi>P. Diaconus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates in his Roman Hiſtory, <hi>lib.</hi> 11. and <hi>Tholoſanus</hi> in his Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, <hi>lib.</hi> 12. <hi>cap.</hi> 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>pag.</hi> 722. records the like, <hi>Pageants</hi> of ſome Jews in <hi>Spaine, anno dom.</hi> 694. and <hi>Cranzius</hi> in his Hiſtory, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>cap.</hi> 14. of ſome Vandals, who after the death of their Proteſtant Prince <hi>Gotſchalcus,</hi> revolted as ſowes to their wallowing, preſently to Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:161846:13"/>
but <hi>ex meliori luto finxit precordia Titan,</hi> it was not ſo with <hi>Inchequin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Yet thus much I prognoſticate further, That as I hear, hee is ſtrongly Epiſcopized, this without queſtion was a great prologue to his Regalizing, as it is indeed judiciouſly obſerved, both by <hi>Melancton</hi> in his Poſtils, <hi>part</hi> I <hi>pag.</hi> 77. And <hi>Strigellius</hi> in his Chroni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, <hi>part.</hi> I. <hi>pag.</hi> 233. that as Princes doe accommodate Religion to the ſplendour of their Courts (as it was glorious to ſee my Lord Biſhop like a Pope in pompe, or a Cardinall with his traine: ſo amongſt moſt Courtiers and Nobles, there be ſome that even in their Religion, <hi>ſerviunt principium cupiditatibus,</hi> doe too much comply with the humours and inclinations of Princes, pinning their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion on the ſleeves of Monarchs, to carry which way they will, as true or falſe, to heaven or to hell; as <hi>Pencer</hi> obſerves in his Chrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall Lectures, <hi>anno</hi> 1570. how far both Peers and people ſympa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thized with <hi>Jeroboam</hi> in his Golden Calves.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, I partly propheſie (though like <hi>Calchas</hi> or <hi>Caſſandra</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps I be ſcarcely believed) that this confederacy of <hi>Inchequin,</hi> a Proteſtant, with the bloody Canniballized Popiſh Rebells, will bee no more ſucceſſefull, then the federacy or confederacy of <hi>Jehoſaphat</hi> with wicked <hi>Ahab,</hi> which we know the iſſue it had, 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 18. 31. and how ſharply God reproved it, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 19<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. even with a threatned wrath: for I believe <hi>Bucholcherus</hi> in his Chronicles, <hi>pag.</hi> 358. That Covenants made with the wicked, are both <hi>inviſa Deo,</hi> hatefull to God, &amp; <hi>pernitioſa hominibus,</hi> dangerous to men: And he that hath bookes to read, and braines to underſtand, ſhall ſee this, not onely affirmed but confirmed in many inſtances both of Chriſtians and Pagans, by <hi>Melancions</hi> Chronology, <hi>lib.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 6. by <hi>Strigellius</hi> in his Chronicles, <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 56. and his Common places, <hi>part.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 414. as alſo by <hi>Chitreus</hi> on <hi>Geneſis pag.</hi> 282. and in his Chronicles of <hi>Sax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ony, lib.</hi> 14. <hi>pag<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 423. and by our Moderne Hiſtorians, our moſt judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Guiccaronie</hi> in his Politicks, <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 29. &amp; <hi>pag.</hi> 100. and <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaeus</hi> in his paſſages <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 52. betwixt the French <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Charles,</hi> whither in this rapſody, for brevity, I refer my Reader, as alſo to <hi>Manl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us</hi> his Common places, <hi>p.</hi> 407. <hi>Strigenitius</hi> his third Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon of the calling of <hi>Jeremy, pag.</hi> 18. and to <hi>Pencers</hi> Hiſtoricall Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, <hi>anno</hi> 1569. <hi>Decemb.</hi> 3. &amp; 1570. <hi>Iuly</hi> 29. where any ſhall ſee Covenants made with Hereticks, Idolaters, men of ſtrange Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, Natures, Religions, to be as proſperous uſually as for hens to hold leagues with hawkes, Iſraelites to joyne in affinities and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacts
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:161846:13"/>
with Canaanites; as Doves with Eagles, and Sheepe with Wolves.</p>
            <p>But once more to retrive my Sprung Woodcock, and to pounce him to ſome purpoſe; as the Poet ſaid, <hi>ſepe Jocum ſepeque bilem veſtri movere tumultus.</hi> I know not whether I ſhall more pitty <hi>Mounſier Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cury</hi> as a witty foole, or be angry with him as a profeſt enemy, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Elimas</hi> the ſorcerer, <hi>Acts</hi> 13. of all goodneſſe and grace; or as <hi>Peter</hi> of <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> in the very gall of bitterneſſe and bond of iniquity, <hi>Acts</hi> 8. Firſt in tearming the Rebells of <hi>Ireland</hi> Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licks (he meanes good Catholick ſubjects as ever man hanged up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his hedge) and with theſe Catholicks forſooth, and the Lord <hi>Taffe,</hi> a profeſt polypragmaticall Papiſt, a great ſtickler in the laſt maſſacre in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and ſtill a firebrand and incendiary in both Climes, he tripudiates that <hi>Inchequin</hi> is to joyne againſt an Army of Sectaries: very good ſtuffe, Chriſt muſt be untrue, his verdict muſt not ſtand, Sathans kingdome muſt be divided by <hi>Mercuries</hi> divinity, his ſervants and agents for his helliſh Hierarchy, muſt like the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of <hi>Cadmus</hi> oppoſe one another, and as the Medianites thruſt their ſwords in the ſides one of another, Sectaries againſt Sectaries, Iriſh againſt Engliſh. 2. Or it may be he meanes the Papiſts in <hi>Ireland</hi> muſt (as they fought for the King before, under that colour) be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed once more for the purging of the Temple from Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency and Presbytery, for the re-eſtabliſhing and re-planting of Epiſcopacy, for ſetting the petty Popes af <hi>Lambeth, London, Lincolne,</hi> and other parts, once more on Cock-horſe to ride to <hi>Dunſtable,</hi> or to the Devill, over the necks, and backs of all zealous, powerfull, and painfull preachers.</p>
            <p>In concluſion for confuſion, they muſt forſooth reforme Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, as Woolves heale and teare ulcerous and rotten ſheep; as clay and mire ſcoure veſſells brighter, as ſoot and inke waſh foule fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces fairer; as Mercury heales green wounds, vinegar ſore eyes, the ſting of an Aſpe takes away the ache in the flea-blowes; all theſe the more increaſing maladies, miſeries, paines, and perplexities, this reforming being as though <hi>Verres</hi> and <hi>Guſman</hi> were appointed Judges to ſcoure their Circuits of Rogues and Thieves, as <hi>Claudius &amp; Clodius,</hi> to reform adulterers, <hi>Meſſalina</hi> and <hi>Paſiphad, Curtizans</hi> Bawds and Concubines, by inflicting corrective mulcts upon them for their incontinency, and to read them directive Lectures for chaſtity.</p>
            <p>But to ſtrike with the maine Hammer, reflect a little on <hi>Mercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> policie, as well as piety, and ſee what a wiſe and well-wiſhing
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:161846:14"/>
worthy Patriot <hi>Mercury</hi> and his Mercurialized ones are to their Country, in that they would bring in under the conduct of <hi>Inche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quin,</hi> now an Army of knowne, reall, forreigne Rebells from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Country, where they are fleſht in blood, to fight for their King forſooth, whom they love as I love their Pope, againſt his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all friends, his meere imaginary foes, the Weſtminſterians, whom <hi>Mercury</hi> marks for Rebells; bringing them in forſooth, into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> to ſide with his Regaliſts againſt Round-heads, with as much wiſdome as the Carians to their coſt brought in <hi>Cyrus</hi> to end their Civill wars; as the Thebans called in the Macedonian <hi>Phillip</hi> to help them againſt the Phocians; as Duke <hi>Boniface</hi> brought into Affrick, <hi>Genſerick</hi> the King of the Vandalls againſt the Emperour <hi>Valens,</hi> as <hi>Leo</hi> the Grecian Emperour fetcht in the Turkes againſt the Bulga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians; as <hi>Laſcus</hi> called in <hi>Solyman</hi> the <hi>Ottoman</hi> into <hi>Hungary</hi> againſt <hi>Fardinand. Theodoſius,</hi> the <hi>Gothes</hi> againſt the <hi>Franckes; Stillico</hi> the <hi>Dur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gundians,</hi> and <hi>Swedes</hi> againſt the <hi>Gothes, Heraclus</hi> the <hi>Arabians</hi> againſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> or the <hi>Spaniards</hi> in moderne times were brought into <hi>Scicily</hi> and <hi>Naples</hi> againſt the French; or as the laſt <hi>Caliph</hi> of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> called <hi>Sarracon,</hi> the laſt Sultan of <hi>Siria,</hi> into his Country againſt <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mericus</hi> the ſucceſſour of <hi>Baldwin</hi> King of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> even with ſuch ſucceſſe as theſe, and many moe, which I could Hiſtorifie from Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours and experiments at this day, may we perhaps bring in for either divided party, either Iriſh, French, Spaniard, or Pope, or any forreigne Nation, as theſe recited felt to their coſt, to fiſh in our troubled waters, to catch ſilver Eeles in our muds, our bloods, like Buzzards to ſwapper at, and teare both Frog and Mouſe fighting, to ſucke our bloods, ſpunge our goods, poſſeſſe our ſeats, and once got in amongſt us, not to get out, more then pitch out of the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome of a Can, ſcarce renſht out with ſilver ſtreams, running as clear as <hi>Tyne</hi> or <hi>Tweed:</hi> as he that will be fully poſſeſt of the prejudice of other ſtates, as the glaſſe of our fates in fetching in forreigne Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to end our controverſies, as the Wolfe to be umpire betwixt the Sheep and the Aſſe, let him read the verdicts of Polititians, and the Tragedies of theſe recited, with numerous moe. In <hi>Bucholche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> his Chronology, <hi>pag.</hi> 389. In <hi>Melanctons</hi> Chronicle, <hi>lib.</hi> 4. <hi>pag.</hi> 301. 443, 444. In <hi>Strigellius</hi> his Chronicle <hi>part.</hi> 1. <hi>pag.</hi> 207. <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>pag.</hi> 60. In <hi>Crutreus</hi> his leſſer Chronicle, <hi>Amor.</hi> 93, 94, 95. <hi>pag.</hi> 44. In <hi>Tholo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanus</hi> his Common-wealth, <hi>lib.</hi> 11. <hi>cap.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 656. In <hi>Bodius</hi> Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 888. In <hi>Patritius</hi> his Common-wealth, <hi>lib.</hi> 9. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it. pag.</hi> 396. As alſo in heatheniſh Authors, chiefly <hi>Polibus, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 15, 16.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:161846:14"/>
And <hi>Heroditus l.</hi> 6. <hi>p.</hi> 163. &amp; <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>p.</hi> 207. which Authours I alleadge as on a ſudden, in two dayes I recollected them, both to diſcover the folly of this frivolous <hi>Mercury,</hi> in ſpinning a web to catch Gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dees, with meere rocke and ſpindle of a naturall wit, without any yarne of reading or judgement, as alſo to muzle or puzle him from barking any more againſt, either the Parliament or the Authours, I alleadge throughout this Rapſody, the Champions againſt his ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vills and ungrounded calumny.</p>
            <p>In the reſt of his Sarriſmes, this <hi>Don quipot</hi> fights as it were with Rams and poaſts, and Wind-mills, for Giants, I meane with his owne meere airy and windy conceits, as the Cat playes with her owne tayle, chiefly he fights as with his owne ſhadow, when as a mad man he caſts his brands at King <hi>Noll,</hi> whom his fellow <hi>Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholicus,</hi> or his <hi>alter ego,</hi> his ſecond ſelfe, plainly calls King <hi>Crumwell,</hi> a man that is not in <hi>rerum natura,</hi> not ſo much as in the orbe of the Moone, nor on the center of the Earth, within the ſphere of our knowledge; for although many meaner men for gifts and place, then the Martiall <hi>Crumwell,</hi> even ſome Country Peaſants, by ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litude of phyſiognomies, have uſurped the names of Kings, as one <hi>Wooldeman</hi> a Miller in <hi>Marchia,</hi> in <hi>Pencers</hi> Chronicles, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>pag.</hi> 60. and in <hi>Lauclavius</hi> his Turkiſh Hiſtory, <hi>pag.</hi> 291. and a <hi>Pſeudo ſinerdis</hi> in <hi>Perſia,</hi> who went long under the name of the ſonne of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> in <hi>Juſtin. pag.</hi> 23. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. and in <hi>Heroditus lib.</hi> 3. 90. and one <hi>Phillip</hi> in <hi>Theſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalia,</hi> a meane Plebeian in the third Punicke war, related by <hi>Florus</hi> in his Epitome, <hi>lib.</hi> 49. 50. &amp; 52. and a Peaſant in <hi>Saxony,</hi> a falſe <hi>Fredericke, anno</hi> 1262. in <hi>Cuſpiman pag.</hi> 440. alſo we know in <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh dayes, what broyles were kindled by <hi>Lambert</hi> and <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kin, Warbecke,</hi> vulgar youths pretented to be of the blood Royall; yet that ever <hi>Crumwell,</hi> or his fame-worthy Generall, called or counted themſelves Kings, or were ſo held or reputed by their Souldiers, ſhall be proved in <hi>Platoes</hi> great yeare, or in the Callends of the Greeks when all Priapized Prieſts, and Friars, and all the veſtall Nuns of <hi>Venus,</hi> live chaſtely together; or when Jeſuitized Papiſts, what ere they pretend ſhall love a Proteſtant Prince ſo wel, unleſſe moulded downe-right their creature, as to ſpare him in the Baſilicall veynes, more then the two French <hi>Henries,</hi> ſo long as they had ever at hand a <hi>junior Faux,</hi> Rivillack <hi>Parry, Lopus</hi> or <hi>Lupus,</hi> with a ponyard, a poyſon, or a piſtoll in his hand, as Treaſon in his heart.</p>
            <p>In his next ſtreines, which deſerve necke ſtreyning, as though he
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:161846:15"/>
were an <hi>Incubus</hi> or <hi>Succubus,</hi> or one of the Colledge of <hi>Bird</hi> or <hi>Merlin,</hi> and Mother <hi>Shipton,</hi> or were ſome Witch, or Conjurer, or had ſome <hi>Mephiſtophiles</hi> or familiar ſpirit, as once Doctor <hi>Fauſtus, Cornelius, Agrippa, Simon Magus,</hi> and other Nicromancers; or at leaſt were ſome judiciall Aſſ-ſtronomer, Aſſ <hi>Colens, Aſtra:</hi> conſulting with the ſtarres, or at beſt ſome Familiſt, and muſhrump Enthuſiaſt, as once <hi>John a Leidan,</hi> and <hi>Munſter</hi> his Prophet; he takes upon him to propheſie, <hi>ſepe malum hoc nobis predixit ab ilice cornix</hi>) as ominouſly and fatally, as the prognoſticks of any ominous Scritchowle, croa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king Raven, or howling dog; yea with as much confidence as any bleſſing, white Witch, Gypſie or Fortune-teller of ſtrange and heavy newes, that we both have it, and muſt have from <hi>France, Scotland, Ireland, Wales,</hi> every part of the Kingdome, and the ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Iſland to: more ſpecially as though he ſhould cry, the Fox gives you warning, and I give you warning to take heed of your Geeſe: this <hi>Iack Iugler,</hi> or <hi>Hocus, Pocus,</hi> ſhootes off a terrible warning-piece, like a <hi>Balaams</hi> curſe, a Papall excommunication comming out, or a <hi>Brutum Fulmen,</hi> to take heed of the 28. of June, for 28. was like to prove a fatall number, to all Parliamentarians, ſuch as theſe <hi>dies nefandi,</hi> theſe unlucky dayes which the Romans held as fatall, in which <hi>Caeſar</hi> was ſtabb'd in the Senate, and in which they loſt ſo much blood and honour in the battells at <hi>Canna</hi> and <hi>Thraſimen,</hi> but <hi>mira Cannat non credenda Poetae,</hi> your Alma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nack is held to be meerly like your ſelfe, a Mercurialized liar, and you are thought to ſtudy onely <hi>Errapater;</hi> for when did you pry into Gods Arke, or were admitted into Gods Cabinet-counſel? If Grandees hold you fitter to be of their Privy (as <hi>Sco<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gan</hi> once to the French King) then of their Privy-counſell, and if you ſcoffe at Plebeians, for perking from plowes and ſhops into <hi>Moſes</hi> his chaire; how dare you perke into Gods chaire, to reveale his ſecrets lockt in his owne decree: ſure as there is a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſting Epitaph of one <hi>Fiddle, That the one and twentieth day of</hi> June, John Fiddle <hi>he went out of tune:</hi> ſo the eight and twenty day of <hi>Iune,</hi> thy Cuckowes note goes out of tune. Much I know the Platoniſts, and Pithagoreans, have aſcribed to numbers, and to their dayes, yea yeares fatall, chiefly to their Climactericalls in their revolutions of ſevens and nines, ominous in the falls of great Peeres and Princes; as much at large is ſaid for numbers by <hi>Cornelius Agrippa, de occulta Philoſophia, lib.</hi> 3. and many inſtances are given by <hi>Levinus L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mnius</hi> in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Booke of the ſecrets of Nature, <hi>cap.</hi> 32. <hi>pag.</hi> 381. and by <hi>Ranzo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vius</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:161846:15"/>
in his Climactericall yeares, <hi>pag.</hi> 227, 228. &amp; <hi>ſeq. Patritius</hi> alſo in his Common-wealth, <hi>lib.</hi> 5. <hi>tit.</hi> 7. <hi>pag.</hi> 234. interpoſeth much to this purpoſe; and for my poore part, I have read how fatall the twenty eighth yeare hath been to many great ones, <hi>Atropos</hi> then cutting ſhort the thread of the lives of <hi>Phillip</hi> King of <hi>Spaine,</hi> father to <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, of <hi>Lodovicke</hi> the ſixt, <hi>Lamdgrave</hi> of <hi>Thuringo,</hi> of <hi>Oſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wald</hi> an Engliſh King, ſonne to <hi>Acha,</hi> ſiſter to <hi>Edmund</hi> call'd the Saint; of Cardinall <hi>Hipolitus medices,</hi> at thoſe yeares poyſoned of <hi>C. Caligula, Caeſar,</hi> ſonne to <hi>Germanicus</hi> ſtabb'd with thirty wounds, of <hi>Iohn Medices,</hi> father to that great <hi>Coſmus</hi> Duke of <hi>Hetraria</hi> ſlaine with a Canon; as alſo of <hi>Perſius</hi> the Satyricall Poet, <hi>Daniel Gricaeus, Hierom Vrſinus,</hi> and many moe, who in the prime and April of their yeares, at the age of twenty eight yeares, acting ſhort parts on the worlds ſtage, were then ſtrucke <hi>non-plus</hi> by death, moſt by a vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent rather then a naturall ſtroke. But for any great diſaſters that have fallne on the twenty eight day of June, I have not ſlept with the Lune: Nor am I verſt ſo in the Skies, To vent with <hi>Mercury</hi> loud lyes.</p>
            <p>But theſe are but the off-ſcums of the wit of this <hi>junior Rombus,</hi> this fritter of fraud, this ſeething pot of iniquity (as I could pay him home in his owne coyne, in retorting jeaſts as ſharpe as the teeth of a Pike, to nip this Gudgeon) at beſt theſe are but <hi>ludicra genii, vel ingenii,</hi> the ſpots of his wit, the playing but the Buffon, or the Monkey, to make himſelfe and others ſport, with his, <hi>Come a loft Jack an Apes with a whim wham:</hi> but in his rhyme-doggerills, which in them have no jot of rhyme nor reaſon, like ſnow in June, and Harveſt out of ſeaſon; in theſe his toothed Satyrs, on his Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphs, or nipping-taphs, as the Countryman miſ-called them, which the malitious momiſt makes on our Parliament men ere they be dead, (who perhaps may live to eat of the Gooſe which grazed on the grave of this Gander of <hi>Gotham</hi>) in theſe he ſhewes himſelfe in his colours indeed, like the devill in his hornes, there he toſſeth them on the pike of his pen, as a baited <hi>Royſton</hi> Bull, the valerous Maſtives; there he acts the parts not of a <hi>Davus</hi> onely to diſturb all, but of a <hi>Demon</hi> a devil to deſtroy all, as <hi>homo homini demon,</hi> he verifies in his damned deſires, that one man is a devill to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in boyling wrath, like wilde fire, and the coals of juniper, ſcarce quenched by dead aſhes: for he ſo far like a ſnarling Fox ſhews his tongue and his teeth, when he is coopt in his chaine, that he cannot worry as he would, that if he could he would <hi>ſevire in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:161846:16"/>
manes,</hi> tyrannize over their very deaths, as the Greeks which abuſed <hi>Hector;</hi> and the Papiſts (in acts fitter for Wolves and Hienaes then Chriſtians) in digging up the dead bodies of <hi>Paulus Fagius,</hi> and of <hi>Peter Martyrs</hi> wife; for whereas in his other Satiricalls, (<hi>his Satyrae ſatirae</hi>) he ſtings like a Serpent (as its ſaid of a Serpent that eats a Serpent) in his deteſtable Epitaph, he proves a Dragon ſpitting wilde-fire; beſides ſome rough paſſages betwixt <hi>Hierom</hi> and <hi>Ruffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus, Chriſoſtome,</hi> and <hi>Ephanus, Eraſmus,</hi> and <hi>Julius Scaliger, Luther</hi> and <hi>Caroloſtadius,</hi> more indeed then well became grave Divines, and modeſt Chriſtians. I have read invectives as ſharp as raizours, and cutting ſwords of <hi>Saluſt,</hi> againſt <hi>Tully, Tully</hi> againſt <hi>Mark Anthony, Varres</hi> and <hi>Cateline, Eſtchines</hi> againſt <hi>Demoſthenes,</hi> and of latter times of <hi>Cocleus</hi> and <hi>Bolſecus</hi> againſt <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> of <hi>Himmimus Ecardus,</hi> and moſt ridged Lutherans againſt Calviniſts, more then againſt Papiſts; of <hi>Stapleton</hi> in his Promptuary, <hi>Faverdentius</hi> upon <hi>Jude, Kelliſon</hi> in his ſcurrilous Survey, and moſt Romiſh <hi>Rabſhekahs</hi> againſt all Proteſtants, chiefly of <hi>Turner</hi> in his orations againſt Queene <hi>Elizabeth:</hi> but as if the ſpirits of all theſe in a Pithagorean tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>migration, with all the Satyricall ſpleen of <hi>Lucian</hi> againſt the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned (called the <hi>Cerberus</hi> of the Muſes) and of <hi>Tom Naſh</hi> againſt the three <hi>Harvies,</hi> marching as though their guts with his Gunpowder tearmes, were infuſed into his eldeſt ſonne of Sathan, as <hi>Polycarpus</hi> called <hi>Marcion,</hi> he ſo ſympathizeth with Sathan in his falſe accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations; all theſe concurring as one (as the venom of all Serpents in one Baſiliske) they could not expreſſe worſe then he is in his damnable Epitaph upon the fictious deaths of the chiefe Ephoriſts of our ſtate; for like an Atheiſt little heeding, nor believing the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pithites and Titles, with which the Scriptures honour them, as of Rulers, Heads, and Elders of the people, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 4. 1, 2. <hi>Num.</hi> 11. 16, 17. <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. 10. Privy-counſellours to Kings, as ſometimes to <hi>Aſhuerus, Heſter</hi> 1. 3. and to the Kings of Iſrael, <hi>Jer.</hi> 26. 10. and conjoyned with them in their Edicts, <hi>Ionas</hi> 3. 7. nor regarding the honourable names of Patritians given to ſuch as they in <hi>Rome,</hi> of Ephoriſts in Lacedemon; of Senators in <hi>Venice,</hi> of great Dons in <hi>Spaine,</hi> of Peers in <hi>France;</hi> of pillars, ribs, ſides, foundation, ſtrength, of the Empire in <hi>Germany;</hi> by the Bull of <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, <hi>Cap.</hi> 3. 12. 24, 26. all theſe honourable and authoritative Titles, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpurned of ſuch blatrant beaſts as this malevolent Timoniſt, as dogs and hogs ſpurne pearles, he ſqueezeth his wits, pumpes his braines, digs as low as hell for gunpowdered calumnies, and bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:161846:16"/>
moe galling, girding, ſtigmatizing opprobries to caſt in their Faces, and on their places, then ever Tailours, Poets, Play<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Perriwig-makers, and Courtiers, borrowed fantaſticalities, or Jewes and Jeſuits new invented poyſons; or as our new Shakers and Seekers, new invented Hereſies and Sects of blacke <hi>Pluto</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe. Oh how he roares as in a Pumpe, though in other paſſages this hot Gameſter play all his trickes at noddy, ever turning up knave oth' Clubs, yet here he trumpes no leſſe then Treaſon, and playes all his prankes at <hi>Loadum,</hi> or Loadhome, loading our wiſeſt, &amp; worthieſt Senatours, with the baſe and bloody imputations of am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition, rebellion, pride, luſt, murther, ſacriledge; and what not? as give the devill an inch, and hee'le take an ell, over ſhooes, over bootes in villany; now that he is in his Rope-rhetoricke in a high way march (like railing Jeſuits from <hi>Tiber</hi> to <hi>Tyburne,</hi> up Gallows gate, and downe Hemp-ſtreet) he cannot get out, he can no more be got out of his tract, then a Carriers horſe in his way to <hi>Dunſtable,</hi> or <hi>Dublin,</hi> or the devills Inne, where he intends to take up his lodging: hence he bites them further with his Theonine teeth, ſharper then Foxes and Badgers, and more poyſoned then the teeth of Vipers and Adders, and ſets his brands and imiſtions upon them of grand Impoſtors, perjured Knaves, out-veying any, otherwiſe <hi>Newgate</hi>-bird, <hi>Pick-hatch, Shoarditch,</hi> or <hi>Turnball</hi>-ſtreet Cockatrice, or the moſt hot-mouthed Scold, and black-mouthed curſing Witch, in all the devills Territories; ſuch blacke and baſe ſtinking ſtuffe he vomits, as would make the Devill himſelfe, the blacke Dog of Hell, ſicke to licke it up: for my part, it ſmells worſe to me, or to any right naſuted man, then any Fox or Fowmart, yea then any carrion, or <hi>aſſafaetida,</hi> as any may read what the blawant beaſt roares out in his reaſonleſſe raging rhymes, in aſperſions more falſe and foule then ever were caſt upon <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> and <hi>Socrates</hi> in <hi>Athens,</hi> on <hi>Cato</hi> himſelfe the marrow of Juſtice, and the two <hi>Scipioes</hi> and other Patriots in <hi>Rome</hi> oft queſtioned by calumniating emulating ſpirits even in the Senate (as well as ours now) yet ever came fairely or ſquarely off, and bore the Bucklers (as ours may doe) and then <hi>rumpantur ilia Codri.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to conclude, I retort theſe his raſcally raylings, with Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thites of honour, yea with this Epitaph of fame, if they ſhould periſh in their projects and proſecutions of the common good, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curia &amp; injuria temporum;</hi> by the ungratefull and ungracious times: yet this <hi>Encomium</hi> is fitter to be ingraven on their graves, then his Roguiſh Rhymes.</p>
            <lg>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:161846:17"/>
               <l>THough <hi>Codrus</hi> guts ſhould burſt aſunder,</l>
               <l>Here be interr'd our ages wonder.</l>
               <l>The fam'd phyſicians of our Seate,</l>
               <l>Recorded with unworthy hate</l>
               <l>Of dog ſicke Times; who not induring</l>
               <l>Their purging pills, did ſnarle their curing;</l>
               <l>Yet their undaunted zeale, ſtood ſhocks,</l>
               <l>And ſtormes of Time, like <hi>Neptunes</hi> Rockes:</l>
               <l>And like the two fixt Poles in Sky,</l>
               <l>They toucht all ſtrings; all wayes did try</l>
               <l>To curbe and cure the maladies</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Albions</hi> felt fear'd Tragedies;</l>
               <l>Both the Kings evill in the head,</l>
               <l>And Gangreens through the body ſpread,</l>
               <l>By ſtrong French Philters and ſlye trickes</l>
               <l>Of Michavillian Empericks:</l>
               <l>The ſurging ſtreames did riſe ſo ſtrong</l>
               <l>From <hi>Po, Rhemes, Tiber;</hi> and ſo throng</l>
               <l>From fluctuate froathy fooles the waves</l>
               <l>In their mad moodes, and Bedlam raves:</l>
               <l>Yea ſo Antipathiz'd was their hate,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt all reformes in Church and State,</l>
               <l>That they are ſwallowed (as by whales</l>
               <l>Juſt <hi>Jonaſſes</hi>) in Tragicke falls:</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Phenix</hi> like burnt in the flame</l>
               <l>Of love and zeale, they ſhall againe:</l>
               <l>Riſe and out live an ancient ſtory,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Albions</hi> Patriots, <hi>Englands</hi> glory;</l>
               <l>Whom Prince, Pope, Peſts, nor vulgars luſt</l>
               <l>Could once divert from Lawes, right, juſt;</l>
               <l>They ſacrific'd their deareſt blood,</l>
               <l>'Gainſt <hi>Englands</hi> ſins, for <hi>Englands</hi> good.</l>
               <l>Let Zoiliſts, Momiſts here defaee them,</l>
               <l>This Epitaph in their urnes ſhall grace them.</l>
               <l>Their honoured aſhes 'gainſt the times</l>
               <l>Shall riſe, for all thy Roguiſh Rhymes.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>And ſo I leave thee, and all thy croaking frogs and ominous Owles and Ravens of thy baſe, blacke, and bloody feather, chiefly thy Comraide Mercury <hi>Bellicus</hi> and <hi>Melancholicus,</hi> ſince as ſtriking two Wood-cocks with one bolt, in putting a hook in thy noſe I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo hook them, you hanging together in one ſubject, like burs, as you deſerve to hang like bells; or reaſty Bacon, much better for hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: for I propheſie, if you hold on to vent your invenomed gals as you do, your libelling lines may cut ſhort the lines of your loathed lives, <hi>dabit Deus his quoq<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> fluvem,</hi> and then you may ſing or ſigh your <hi>Lacrimae per varios caſus, per tot diſcrimina rerum, tendemus in laqueum:</hi>
            </p>
            <lg>
               <l>Through different, baſe, bad courſes, all our hopes</l>
               <l>Tending, their ending have, in Tibornes ropes.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:161846:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
